<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe discourse, declaring the impiety and unlawfulnesse of the new Covenant with the Scots. Together with the Covenant it selfe.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77428</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E73_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14064</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859606</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859606</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155472</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77428)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155472)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 13:E73[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe discourse, declaring the impiety and unlawfulnesse of the new Covenant with the Scots. Together with the Covenant it selfe.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Henry Hall],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name and place of publication from Madan.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "26: Octob." "Oxon".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643). --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155472:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155472:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE DISCOVRSE, DECLARING The impiety and unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the new COVENANT with the SCOTS.</p>
            <p>Together with the <hi>Covenant</hi> it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:155472:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155472:2"/>
            <head>The new League and Covenant with the SCOTS.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E Noblemen, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens. Burgeſſes, Miniſters of the Goſpell, and Commons of all ſorts in the Kingdom of</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>by the providence of God, living under one King, and being of one Reformed Religion, having before our Eyes the Glory of God, and the Advancement of the Kingdome of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, the Honour and Happineſſe of the Kings Majeſty, and His Poſteritie, and the true publike Liberty, Safety, and Peace of the Kingdomes, wherein every ones private Condition is included; And calling to minde the Treacherous and Bloody Plots, Conſpiracies, Attempts, and Practiſes of the Enemies of God, againſt the true Religion and Profeſſors thereof, in all places, eſpecially in theſe three Kingdomes, ever ſince the Reformation of Religion; And how much their Rage, Power, and Preſumption, are of late, and at this time increaſed and exerciſed, whereof the deplorable Eſtate of the Church and Kingdom of</hi> Ireland, <hi>the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Eſtate of the Church and Kingdome of</hi> England, <hi>and the dangerous Eſtate of the Church and Kingdome of</hi> Scotland, <hi>are preſent and publike Teſtimonies. We have now at laſt (after other meanes of Supplication, Remonſtrance, Proteſtations, and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings) for the Preſervation of our ſelves and our Religion, from utter ruine and deſtruction, according to the commendable practiſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155472:3"/>of theſe Kingdomes in former times, and the example of Gods Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in other Nations, after mature deliberation, reſolved and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to enter into a mutuall and ſolemne League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, wherein we all ſubſcribe, and each one of us for himſelf, with our hands lifted up to the moſt High God, do ſwear,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. THat we ſhall ſincerely, really, and conſtantly, through the grace of God, indeavour in our ſeverall Places and Callings, The preſervation of the Reformed Religion in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, againſt our common Enemies, the Reformation of Religion in Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government, according to the Word of God, and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches; And ſhall indeavour to bring the Churches of God in the three Kingdomes to the neereſt Conjunction and Uniformity in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Confeſſion of Faith, Forme of Church Government, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory for Worſhip and Catechiſing; That we and our poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie after us, may as Brethren live in Faith and Love, the Lord may delight to dwell in the midſt of us.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That we ſhall in like manner, without reſpect of Perſons, indeavour the exterpation of Popery, Prelacy, (that is, Church-Government, by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, their Chancellours, and Commiſſaries, Deanes, Deanes and Chapters, Archdeacons, and all other Eccleſiaſticall Officers depending on that Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,) Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſme, Prophaneſſe, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall be found to be contrary to ſound Doctrine, and the Power of Godlineſſe, leſt we partake in other mens ſins, and thereby be in danger to receive of their Plagues; and that the Lord may be one, and his Name one in the three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p n="3">III. We ſhall with the ſame ſincerity, reality, and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in our ſeverall Vocations, indeavour with our Eſtates and Lives, mutually to preſerve the Rights and Priviledges of the Parliaments, and the Liberties of the Kingdoms, and to preſerve and defend the Kings Majeſties Perſon, and Authority, in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155472:3"/>preſervation and defence of the true Religion and Liberries of the Kingdomes, That the World may bear Witneſſe with our Conſciences of our Loyalty, and that we have no Thoughts or Intentions to diminiſh His Majeſties juſt Power and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. We ſhall alſo with all faithfulneſſe indeavour the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of all ſuch as have beene, or ſhall be Incendiaries, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, or evill Inſtruments, by hindering the Reformation of Religion, dividing the King from his People, or one of the Kingdoms from another, or making any faction, or parties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the People contrary to this League and Covenant; That they may be brought to publike Tryall, and receive condigne puniſhment, as the degree of their offences ſhall require or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, or the ſupreame Judicatories of both Kingdoms, reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, or others having power from them for that effect, ſhall judge convenient.</p>
            <p n="5">V. And whereas the happyneſſe of a bleſſed Peace between theſe Kingdoms, denyed in former times to our Progenitours, is by the good providence of God granted unto us, and hath beene lately concluded and ſetled by both Parliaments; We ſhall each one of us, according to our Place and Intereſt indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, That they may remaine conjoyned in a firm Peace and Union to all Poſteritie; and that Juſtice may be done upon the wilfull oppoſers thereof, in manner expreſſed in the precedent Article.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. We ſhall alſo according to our Places and Callings, in this common Cauſe of Religion, Libertie, and Peace of the Kingdomes, aſſiſt and defend all thoſe that enter into this League and Covenant, in the maintaining and purſuing thereof; and ſhall not ſuffer our ſelves directly, or indirectly, by whatſoever combination, perſwation, or terrour, to be devided and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from this bleſſed Union and Conjunction, Whether to make defection to the contrary part, or to give our ſelves to a deteſtable indifferency or neutralitie in this Cauſe, which ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155472:4"/>much concerneth the glory of God, the good of the Kingdoms and honour of the King; but ſhall all the dayes of our lives, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, and conſtantly continue therein againſt all oppoſition, and promote the ſame according to our Power, againſt all Lets and Impediments whatſoever: And what we are not able to ſuppreſſe, or overcome, we ſhall reveale and make known, that it may be timely prevented or removed. All which we ſhall do, as in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>And becauſe theſe Kingdomes are guilty of many ſinnes and provocations againſt God and His Son leſus Chriſt, as is too manifeſt by our preſent diſtreſſes and dangers, the fruits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; We profeſſe and declare before God and the World, our unfained deſire to be humbled for our owne ſinnes, and for the ſinnes of theſe Kingdomes, eſpecially that we have not as we ought, valued the ineſtimable benefit of the Goſpell; That we have not laboured for the Purity and Power thereof; and that we have not endeavoured to receive Chriſt in our Hearts, nor to walke worthy of him in our lives, which are the cauſes of other ſinnes and Tranſgreſſions, ſo much abounding amongſt us; And our true and unfained purpoſe, deſire, and endeavour for our ſelves and all others, under our Power and Charge both in publike and in private, in all duties we owe to God and man, to amend our lives, and each one to goe before another in the example of a reall Reformation, That the Lord may turne away his wrath and heavy indignation, and eſtabliſh theſe Churches and Kingdomes in Truth and Peace. And this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant we make in the preſence of Almightie God, the ſearcher of all Hearts, with a true intention to performe the ſame, as we ſhall anſwer at that great day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhal be diſcloſed; moſt humbly beſeeching the Lord to ſtrengthen us by his holy Spirit for this end; And to bleſſe our deſires and proceedings with ſuch ſucceſſe, as may be deliverance &amp; ſafety to his People, and incouragement to the Chriſtian Churches, groaning under, or in danger of the yoak of Antichriſtian Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, to joyne in the ſame or like Aſſociation and Covenant, To the glory of God, the Inlargement of the Kingdom of Ieſus Chriſt, and the Peace and Tranquility of Chriſtian Kingdomes and Common-Wealths.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:155472:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A briefe Diſcourſe, declaring the impiety and unlawfulneſſe of the new COVENANT with the</hi> Scots.
<list>
                  <item>Keepe not thou ſilence, O God: hold not thy peace, and be not ſtill, O God.</item>
                  <item>For lo, thine enemies make a tumult: and they that hate thee, have lift up the head.</item>
                  <item>They have taken crafty counſell againſt thy people, and conſulted againſt thy hidden ones.</item>
                  <item>They have ſaid, come, and let us cut them off from being a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: that the name of Iſrael may be no more in remembrance.</item>
                  <item>For they have conſulted together with one conſent: they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate againſt thee.</item>
                  <item>Mine enemies reproach me all the day, and they that are mad are ſworne againſt me.</item>
                  <item>For they ſpeake againſt thee wickedly, and thine enemies take thy name in vaine.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe were once the complaints of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> againſt Gods enemies and his in thoſe times. But now they may be juſtly, alas too juſtly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up by the King and His faithfull Subject; in theſe times, againſt the contrivers and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of that monſtrous Rebellion, which hath beene the deformed and unnaturall iſſue that the helliſh copulation of Satan, with this wicked and adulterous genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the very lees and dreggs of almoſt exhauſted time hath
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155472:5"/>brought forth. It is a monſter indeed, made up of many mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, every limbe or part of it is as it were a ſeverall portent, preſaging without the great mercy of God, a generall ruine to this poore nation, in all that it can ſtile good; lawes, lives, religion, ſoules, government, order, plenty, ſafety, honour, and that in the ruines whereof, if not the ſubſtance, yet the beauty and comfort of all the reſt muſt needs be buried the happy peace of this Kingdome. A monſter every day almoſt growing more and more monſtrous, ever and anon contracting not onely more ſtature, but (wherein it out-does all the moſt groſſe errours of nature, if I may ſo call them) new limbes, new organs, and members of confuſion, and I would it did not out ſtrip them in one thing more. Nature doth ſeldome uſe to maintaine her errours, and therefore though I know not how ſhe brings them forth, yet ſhe is not wont to give them a long life, which may ſeeme a kind of recantation of nature; ſhe makes haſt to ſcrape out thoſe blots which ſhe hath made. If they be long-lived it is as it were another wonder, and ſo another multiplyed errour of nature, (when I ſpeake of the errour of nature, I meane the miſapplication or diſordered working of ſecond cauſes.) But this, oh it hath lived too too long already, and yet it appeares to be ſtill too youthfull, ſince it is not yet come unto its full ſtature. It is of ſo ſtrange a continuance, as well as of ſad and uncouth importance, that we could ſcarce tell whether it were a Comet or a Starre; but that wee diſcover it by it's low region wherein it moves, and by its irregular motion, and by that blazing traine of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes at the tayle of it, to have no place amongſt the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bodies, as ſome mad Aſtronomers of our age would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us: but that, as it is raiſed from thoſe foggy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſome vapours, that not the earth or water, but even hell it ſelfe hath belcht forth, to the confuſion and deſtruction of mankinde; ſo we are ſure it will not ſtill continue, but will at length waſt and conſume it ſelfe, and fall downe, though with ſuch a ſtench and evill influence, that may perhaps ſuffocate many thouſands that are about it.</p>
            <p>Much hath beene done, and by skilfull hands, towards the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155472:5"/>anatomy and deſcription of this monſter; and no wonder if ſome have met with damps from it in endeavour, like thoſe that open fowle and corrupted bodies, which many times ſend out thoſe maligne vapours, that are ready to poyſon thoſe that have attempted it. I my ſelfe have had my ſhare of this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, and yet when the common good calls for it, in the care we muſt have for the preſervation of publique dangers, though to the perill of our particular ſafeties, wee muſt not deſiſt from the worke. I dare not undertake to expoſe unto your view all the deformities of this ſtrange prodigie. I doubt it hath not yet all its parts and members: whileſt it ſtill lives we can never ſay, we have fully decyphered it. And though we would very faine kill it by diſſection, yet as it is in the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all practiſe of thoſe that anatomize bodies, to do it when they are dead; ſo you muſt looke for the perfect worke in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſection of this when it is dead too: it is too unquiet a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to ſuffer it before, and too increaſing to be capable of it.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the horrible compoſure of it is ſo various and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plexed, that it is very hard to undertake it.</p>
            <p>That which I have to doe at this preſent, is to ſet forth unto you the ſtrange language of this beaſt. We reade of a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous beaſt in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that had a mouth given unto it ſpeaking great things, and blaſphemies: <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.5. And ſurely ſuch is the language of this monſter, eſpecially in this ſtrange and horrid <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Oath,</hi> which they have of late taken upon them, and commended unto others; for can there be any greater blaſphemy then to offer God for ſecurity unto Sathan, to forge his hand and counterfeit his ſeale, as it were to an obligation to binde men over to the Devill. We reade of it as a great aggravation of ſinne, that men frame ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity by a Law: This they have done too as farre as in them lyes, but not content with this, they have now proceeded far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to frame iniquity by an Oath and Covenant. That as they kill mens bodies on the one ſide, ſo they may deſtroy ſoules too
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155472:6"/>on the other; as if they would goe about to confute our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, where he telleth us, that men are able onely to deſtroy the body, and doe no more, and ſhew that they can in ſome ſenſe deſtroy both body and ſoule in hell. My deſire is to lay open this miſchiefe before the people, that they may take heed how they are entrapped in ſo dangerous a ſnare, wherein you muſt not looke for ſo exact a diſcovery as might have beene made, but ſuch, as I was able in great haſt to make of it, being deſirous to apply a ſpeedy prevention, though with leſſe ſerious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition unto ſo dangerous an evill, and that plainly to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of the meaneſt of the people, not doubting but that thoſe that have judgement will be able to diſcover more in it of themſelves: my ayme is to ſhew the impiety of this Oath, which doth appeare unto us in theſe ſeverall heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, it is unlawfull in the manner of it.</item>
               <item>Secondly, in the matter of it.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, in the end of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, in the manner of undertaking it, as it is againſt the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the King: And as it is an entrance into a new League with a forreine Nation without His Majeſties conſent.</p>
            <p>Firſt it is againſt the Authority of the King, which we are all bound to maintaine, in that it is undertaken without His Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; for whatſoever is undertaken without that power which is requiſite thereunto, is againſt that Authority: for as that which cannot derive it ſelfe from God, who hath ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame authority in the ordering of Religion as in all other things, is againſt the ſupreame and abſolute authority of God. So that which cannot derive it ſelfe from the King in matter of Government, when He is ſupreame under God, is againſt the authority of the King, and ſo an irregular and diſorderly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe. For as no animal motion in the body but hath its force and power from the head in the body, ſo there can be no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly publike motion in the State, that hath not its force and influence from the King, who is ſupreame Head under God of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155472:6"/>the body Politique. And herein it is againſt the Oaths of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeance and Supremacy, which bindeth men to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance and preſervation of the Kings authority as ſupreame.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is ſinfull in the manner of it, as it is an entrance into a new League with a forreine Nation, without the conſent of the King, who by the Law and conſtitution of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is of abſolute and ſupreame power in ſuch matters, at leaſt ſo farre, that it cannot, or at leaſt ought not to be done without him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in the manner of taking it: if it be not lawfull, yet it is uncouth and ſtrange, performed by a ceremony of lifting up their hands unto God, as they call it. But we may juſtly ſay by lifting up their hands againſt God, ſince their hands are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lift up againſt Gods ſubſtitute, and againſt that authority that God hath placed in him. But indeed this Ceremony was moſt fit for their purpoſe, moſt correſpondent unto their drift and purpoſe, and doth excellently decypher that buſineſſe they have in hand, and which they meant to ſtrengthen &amp; corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate by this Covenant, even the lifting up of their hands againſt the Lords annointed: which they did well not to ſweare to upon the Bible or Evangeliſts, ſince it is a deſigne directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the whole drift of that holy Doctrine.</p>
            <p>But in the ſecond place it is not onely peccant in the manner, either of taking or undertaking, but much more in the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of it.</p>
            <p>I might ſay ſomething of the ſtrange inverted method, whereby they ſhew us how they meane to turne things upſide downe: Priviledges of Parliament, and Liberties of Subjects, being put before the Authority and Perſon of the King; but we could pardon ſuch <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as theſe, were it not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted more in their actions than in their expreſſions. But not to inſiſt upon this.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:155472:7"/>
            <p>It is peccant in the matter in three maine and principall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. As it is againſt reaſon.</item>
               <item>2. As againſt Scripture.</item>
               <item>3. As it is againſt their owne conſciences.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. It is againſt reaſon that they ſweare to maintaine the Diſcipline and Government of <hi>Scotland</hi> in that Church, and this is againſt reaſon in two reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe thereby they intrude into thoſe things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long not unto them, and are <hi>in alienâ rep. curioſi,</hi> ſince they have no more power to order and diſpoſe of matters in the <hi>Scotch</hi> Nation, then the <hi>Scots</hi> have to order and diſpoſe the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of this. But hereby indeed the <hi>Scots</hi> and they have ſet up a pretry trade and traffique of invaſion; ſince, as the <hi>Scots</hi> by their incitement have moſt unjuſtly and unreaſonably taken upon to order matters in this Kingdome, which hath no depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon them, nor is any way under their Government: ſo they have hereby made themſelves in the tenour of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, a kinde of Moderatours and Governours of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Which notwithſtanding we verily beleeve that Nation will hardly admit of.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is againſt reaſon that they ſhould undertake to keepe that Diſcipline or Government unalterable in another Nation, which all ſound Chriſtians hold, at leaſt in many things to be alterable, and which they themſelves (as it ſeemes by the forme of the Oath) durſt not undertake to ty themſelves unto; certainly herein they are runne into the ſelfe ſame errour, of which they themſelves (if I miſtake not) taxed the late Oath of the Synod, and have tyed themſelves unalterably to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that which may and ought to be altered upon the exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Church. And ſo they have bound themſelves by a ſacred vow, not onely to a thing unneceſſary, and no way ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, in that ſingularity in which they are bound to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155472:7"/>it, but alſo to withſtand the lawfull ſupply of the poſſible and probable neceſſities of the Church. Beſides this, they had beſt be well aſſured that all that they have ſworne to maintaine in that Diſcipline and Government, be agreeable to Gods Word.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is againſt Scripture, that men ſhould binde themſelves to that which is uncertaine; or joyne in a Covenant, the ſenſe whereof is dubious: and wherein they doe by no meanes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and that in the conſcience of their knowne and palpable diſagreement. This is not to ſweare according to Gods rule, in juſtice, judgement, and truth; nor anſwerable to that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere dealing which God looketh for in the taking of an Oath. They that agree upon the words, but differ about the meaning, may be ſo farre from being ſaid to joyne in a Covenant, that they may perhaps ſweare one againſt another in their ſeverall and contrary expoſitions and acceptions.</p>
            <p>Now ſuch is this Oath, that it is neither certaine nor cleare, it being in a part thereof ſet down in thoſe ſtale termes which are capable of a million of interpretations, as when they ſwear to promote the reformation of the Church of England, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Word of God, and the beſt Reformed Churches. What certainty I beſeech you is there in this Oath? or at leaſt, what unity is in it? were they or are they yet all agreed that have taken it: what that reformation is, or what Churches they are that are beſt reformed? Doth not the Independent meane one thing, and the Presbyterian another? Are the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts and Browniſts agreed upon this point? Nay ſurely, we may ſafely ſay, they have ſworn contrary one to another in their ſeverall ſenſes: howſoever one hath ſaid very well of them, or at leaſt of ſome of them: that they agree very well in their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, that is, in ſuch termes that will ſerve all their turnes: The very ſtudied tricke of the holy Tridentine Counſell. But is not this arch colluſion with God, and with one another? Oh my brethren, I beſeech you remember, God is not mocked, you
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155472:8"/>may muffle your ſelves and others, but you cannot blind the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly it is againſt conſcience ſince if the one halfe of thoſe that joyne in other things no more warrantable, ſhall or have joyned in the taking of this Covenant it is not probable that they have or can do it as they are diſpoſed with the conſent or to the ſatisfaction of their conſciences. Or I would gladly know of thoſe various Sectaries as oppoſite un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one another as they are both unto the truth. Whether they all like the Scotch Diſcipline and Government, which they ſweare to maintaine in that Nation, or no, let them now lay their hands upon their hearts, and feele how it beates, if they do like it, why durſt they not ſweare to introduce it here, as well as to defend it there, but that they muſt be pleaſed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved at once with theſe Generall Termes according to the beſt reformed Churches. And with that limitation, as neere as may be unto the Diſcipline and Government of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Oh fy upon this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this fond Glozing, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouring of men in things of ſo ſacred a nature.) But if it be ſo that they do not approve of it, as it is well knowne they do not many of them: with what conſcience can they ſweare to maintaine that in another Nation, which they themſelves in in their judgements diſapprove and condemne as unlawfull and diſagreable to the word of God? Let our independent Brethren and others anſwere me this queſtion. If any ſay that the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Government of <hi>Scotland</hi> may be beſt for that Nation, and yet not ſo convenient for ours. I confeſſe it might ſo be that one kind of Diſcipline in ſome things or circumſtances might fit one Nation and yet be inconvenient for another. But away with theſe refuges. Speake your conſciences ſpeake plainely and do not complement in Covenants. Do you beleeve I meane all you independents, Anabaptiſts, &amp;c: that have or ſhall be called to take this holy bond. Do you all beleeve that the Scotch Diſcipline and Government is the beſt for that acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or do you not beleeve it is in it ſelfe defective if not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the word of God in your ſenſe? I am confident you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155472:8"/>cannot deny but you do. With what conſcience then could you, if you have or can you if you have not, enter into an oath to maintaine that Diſcipline, and Government, any where, which your conſciences perſwade you is not the beſt not good, not agreeable to the word and the will of God? Is not this to pertake with other mens ſinnes, and to joyne with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers againſt that which you call the Kingdome of Chriſt? But here you may ſee the crafty dealing of theſe men, that had the framing and contriving of this covenant. They knew well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough with whom they had to do. And whom they are to depend on for the purſuance of their deſignes. The Scots on the one ſide, much woed, and Courted by them. The various ſectaries and diſagreeing humoriſts on the other ſide. Theſe both muſt be pleaſed, Though God be never ſo much diſpleaſed. And therefore to ſatisfy the Scots and to draw them into this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, the Scottiſh diſcipline and government muſt be maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and all muſt ſweare to that there, though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience deny it. alas it is but to comply with their loving bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. and yet to leave roome for the fond and enterteining hopes of their ſeverall Chimera's which the Sectaries here have dream't of. They muſt be ſatisfied with more Generall termes here. There ſhall be no particular Government or diſcipline ſet downe, but according to the beſt Reformed Churches. which the Anabaptiſt may ſtill conceive to be for him, the Browniſt for him, the Lutherane for him, The Scottiſh for him, yea and the Papiſt for him too, were it not that they have daſht his hopes in another clauſe: onely indeed to pleaſe the Scotts a little more, as thoſe from whom they looke for much benefit. This reformation of <hi>England,</hi> according to the beſt Reformed Churches, muſt be framed as nere as may be to the Scots, were it not ſo ſad a buſineſſe as it is, ſure a man would even laugh to ſee what is behind the Curtaine. And yet this is the holy Covenant.</p>
            <p>The laſt of all good covenants is the glory of God. This you ſee palpably is to pleaſe and engage men.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:155472:9"/>
            <p>The intermediate aime of a good Covenant ſhould be the peace of Gods people. This is like to breede no peace amongſt them that take it. ſince in that latitude which is allowed them they are like to finde roome enough, when they have done ſlaughtering others, to draw their ſwords upon one another in the aſſerting of their ſeverall beſt reformations againſt one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. And God helpe the poore Church of <hi>England,</hi> if it muſt never have peace till they ſhall be agreed. And indeed God helpe it howſoever. But alas this is not all, it is moſt cleare that the end of this covenant, is ſo farre from peace, that it is purpoſely undertaken for the maintenance of a moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid civill warre, and rebellion, and for the engageing of a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne nation, to helpe to butcher the poore people of this land.</p>
            <p>So groſſe and palpable an impiety and deceiving of the truſt that the King and people placed in thoſe that have the maine ſway of the buſineſſes. That I wonder they ſhould any longer doate upon ſo open and profeined a deſigne for their ruine, an enterpriſe that if it ſhould proceed, would make the Authors and Contrivers of it infamous amongſt the moſt barbarous Cannibals, for expoſing their owne Prince and people to be a prey to be devoured by an externall fire, rather then they ſhould any of them ſurvive to ſee the defeate of their ambitious purpoſes.</p>
            <p>Surely I can thinke upon no better a Motto for this bloudy Covenant, and the deſigne that hangs upon it. Then that verſe of the Poet. <hi>Flectere ſi nequeo ſuperos Acheronta movebo.</hi> And yet they ſweare too to diſcover all thoſe that ſhall divide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Prince and the people. But does any man beleeve that they meane to accuſe their owne fellow or to arrayne themſelves at the barre of Juſtice?</p>
            <p>I had like to have overſeene one feature of this beutifull Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, And that is one excellent and neceſſary limitation, that they have annexed unto that part of the oath, wherein they ty themſelves to defend the perſon and authority of the King: A man would thinke and reade no farther that ſome ſtrange fit
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155472:9"/>were come on them of being good Subjects to their Prince. But they'll be ſure of a Gap to get out at there.</p>
            <p>The Liberties of Subjects, and Priviledges of Parliament, muſt be abſolutely and peremptorily maintained, though with the Ruine of Religion and all not a ſyllable of limitation there. But the Kings perſon and his authority muſt be maintained, in preſervation and defence of the true Religion, and in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Kingdome (not a word of the Law in the whole oath. You may ſee by that how they meane to governe) and what doe you thinke is the meaning of this? Surely 'tis no rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle that needs no <hi>O Edipus</hi> to interpret it. 'Tis too cleere the purpoſe is to leave the people at liberty, to kill the Kings per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and to trample on his authority, whenſoever they ſhall conceive that he oppoſeth that religion which they ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be true, or that be intrencheth upon any the leaſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Subjects. So that every errour in a Sectary may upon the point bring a Religious Kings life into queſtion. And every miſtake in policy of the ignorant people, or miſinterprati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Kings Actions by the malicious, may for all this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant pull His Crowne off His head, and let His royall bloud out of his heart too, Oh what an excellent Proviſion is this, and yet they will have the world to beare witneſſe of their loyalty. Here's fuell for an eternall fire if it were poſſible of an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſucceſſion of diviſions and miſcheifes betweene the King, and the people. Chriſtianity teacheth us to ſubmit unto Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants. Yea unto heathens if in authority, in reſpect of Gods ordinances, but theſe men are wiſer and holier then God. they are not ſuch fooles as the Apoſtles and Primitive Chriſtiſtians to ſubmit upon the meere command of Chriſt, unto thoſe that oppreſt them, and ſought their ruine. But I pray God make us ſuch fooles as they were. The wiſedome of this world is fooliſhneſſe with God. I had rather be a foole with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> then wiſe with the beſt of them.</p>
            <p>I commend unto them the ſaying of <hi>Tertullian, Sapiens Deo non eris niſi ſtultus ſaeculo fucris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much more might be ſaid, but I hope this may ſuffice.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:155472:10"/>
            <p>And ſo theſe haſty obſervations I Commend unto the Reader, for his caution and converſion, upon theſe impreſſions that a ſingle reading of this covenant left with mee, with theſe two rules.</p>
            <p>If thou art not ſnared keepe thy ſelfe free.</p>
            <p>If thou haſt taken an unlawfull Vow. Thou hadſt better breake it with <hi>David,</hi> then keepe it with <hi>Herod.</hi> Thy Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban will never ſalue thy diſobedience to thy Common-father, which is thy Prince. and ſo I pray God direct all our hearts, for the glory of his name, and good of his Church and people, And diſcover and defeate all contrary deſignes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:155472:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
